<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A conference of some Christians in church-fellow-ship, about the way of Christ with his people, and the result therefrom. This serveth only by way of introduction to take off the reproaches, that are cast upon pastour and people, whose earnest care and endeavour is to walke with a right foote in that holy way. Which is held forth here by the light of the sacred Scripture, as it appeares unto them, and how curious and circumspect their walke should be, who pretend to it, and to walke therein. The scandalls in and against the way are removed as they could be.</title>
            <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E868_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207653</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866691</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866691</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118975</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96887)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118975)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 131:E868[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A conference of some Christians in church-fellow-ship, about the way of Christ with his people, and the result therefrom. This serveth only by way of introduction to take off the reproaches, that are cast upon pastour and people, whose earnest care and endeavour is to walke with a right foote in that holy way. Which is held forth here by the light of the sacred Scripture, as it appeares unto them, and how curious and circumspect their walke should be, who pretend to it, and to walke therein. The scandalls in and against the way are removed as they could be.</title>
                  <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed according to order for Henry Cripps, in Popes-head-Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Ezekias Woodward.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "By Hezek: Woodward. ffeb: 13".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118975:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CONFERENCE OF Some Chriſtians in Church-fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, about the way of Chriſt with His people, and the Reſult therefrom.</p>
            <p>This ſerveth only by way of <hi>Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction</hi> to take off the Reproaches, that are caſt upon Paſtour and people, whoſe earneſt <hi>care and Endeavour is to walke with a right foote in that Holy way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which is held forth here by the light of the ſacred Scripture, as it appeares unto them, and how Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Circumſpect their walke ſhould be, who pretend to it, and to walke therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſcandalls in and againſt the way are removed as they could be.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>For our ſelves Brethren, our Conſcience ſufficeth, but for you our Name alſo had need to be pretious, and honourable; for we would have our words ſavour ſweetly with you, then ſo muſt our name alſo.</hi> 
               <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Stand in the wayes, and ſee, and aske for the old pathes, which is the good way, and walke therein, and yee ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules; But they ſaid, we will not walke therein.</hi> 
               <bibl>Jer. 6. 16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>He that doth Truth cometh to the Light that his deedes may be made manifeſt that they are wrought in God,</hi> 
               <bibl>Joh: 3. 21.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed according to Order for <hi>Henry Cripps,</hi> in <hi>Popes-head-Alley.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118975:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118975:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A RES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LT</hi> Of a Serious Debate firſt with our ſelves alone and apart, ſeeking God in theſe matters; to Whom Interpretations doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long. Then altogether taking our Paſtour with us to ſeeke-out the truth of the matters in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to a cleare reſolution to thoſe four Queſtions, before ſpecified in the Epiſtle to the Reverend Miniſters, propoſed to us by a reverend and <hi>godly Miniſter, requiring a Reaſon from us of our way and practiſe therein.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Introduction, <hi>Sheweth in the Entrance into it, and cloſe of it, the occaſion and ſcope of this Conference; It ſerveth alſo to vindicate our Paſtour from the Reproaches of wicked men, and jealouſies of the Godly againſt him. And to justifie the Truth of the way, and of our walke therein to be according to the mind of God expreſſed in His Word; our deſire alſo and endeavour to walke therein in all pleaſing before Him.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Honourable;</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or ſo you are, if you are pretious in our Lords eyes; You were pleaſed to ſtoop very low, and ſo an humble perſon can doe; and yet lower if need be, when you turned in to me, <hi>leſſe indeed, then the leaſt of all Saints,</hi> which, is as little as can be; And yet I hope, as I pray, not leſſe in any ones eye, than I am in my own. But
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118975:3"/> whatever I am, by the grace of God I am what I am. Now to the buſineſſe you were pleaſed to propoſe to mee, and require reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from mee thereunto. Theſe, to my beſt remembrance, you called <hi>Circumſtantials</hi> onely, matters of fact, rather than of faith, of an inferiour nature and degree, which may be done or left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, and yet therein walking up to our light, the Command of God is not broken, nor the bond of love with men: And yet to ſpeake a word to this in paſſage onely, I humbly conceive even in theſe matters decency and order muſt be obſerved, and if we looke our worke ſhould finde acceptance with the Lord, it muſt be done in faith alſo; for howſoever the worke be, wee ſuppoſe it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateth to God, and his ſervice, and but a Circumſtance about the worke, rather than of the nature, eſſence, or ſubſtance of the ſame, yet all this falleth under a command, and failing herein, our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is marred, being not performed <hi>after the due order:</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">We may ſay of Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as of Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, theſe have the leaſt entitie, but they have the greateſt efficacie.</note> Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances carry much in our matters with men, much more in warre, they carry all with God, theſe make all or marre all; theſe overthrow our actions, if they be not rightly and duly obſerved; For the Lord ſtands as much upon Circumſtances, as he doth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dutyes. Hee will have them done, and well done, after <hi>the due manner, and order,</hi> by himſelfe preſcribed, or elſe as well undone; becauſe the ſame Lord, that commanded the matter, commanded alſo the manner of our ſervice; indeed the manner is all. But to let this paſſe for the preſent.</p>
               <p>The things you charged upon mee to give you an account of, as to my faith therein and practiſe about them, were to my think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Lord howſoever in common account, and thoughts of others, highly relating to the glory of God, the beauty of his holineſſe, the peace and welfare of his people, ſuch like or the ſame with theſe, mentioned in the title page, and in the Epiſtle to the Rev: Miniſters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>TO theſe things you deſired me, yea you charged mee to give you my opinion; and if in the <hi>Negative,</hi> then to give you the reaſon of my Contrary Judgement unto yours; I tooke this at the firſt hearing, and ſo doe ſtill, to be, a matter too high for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118975:3"/> mee; and indeed, at that preſent was minded, how ever you char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged mee, not to meddle in it; leaſt, as was ſaid of one, you know by whom, <hi>A good cauſe ſhould have a weake Defendant:</hi> Yet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on after-thoughts, and taking Counſell with God, upon whom the Creature depends every moment for his being, and for all his good he hath; and quickly after communing with my brethren, in Fellowſhip with me, about it, as I beleeve your intent, and I am aſſured my duty was to doe; and taking our Miniſter with us, and ſeeking to God againe altogether, we reſolved by the helpe of his grace, to endeavour to give you an account of our matters, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your demands; and, as our God ſhould be pleaſed to give in to us, to give forth to you, keeping all along as cloſe to Him, and His Word, as poſſibly, through the ſupply of His grace, wee can; So you ſee now what is done, and wee are full of hope, ſith it was our full deſire and endeavour, you will finde our words ſo ordered all along, how weakly ſoever, and our matters ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the ſtrength of his grace, which wee have ſought for, as that you will conclude of us, That wee are as unwilling to give any offence to your worthy ſelfe, or any other of your brethren in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice with you, as much honoured by us as well you can thinke, as wee would be to offend the Apple of our Eye; and rather breake our owne bones, then be a meanes, or juſt occaſion to breake the peace of the Church, or of any good man there: ſo you will not account the whole Nation with every Pariſh a Church; and the rich man, the good man, and beſt amongſt them there: If theſe or any one of theſe are pleaſed, God is infinitely diſpleaſed. We ſeek not to pleaſe men, but God. And pleaſing Him, we cannot thinke we can diſpleaſe any good-man. The words we reade, <hi>Caent:</hi> 2. 7. together with the Note on the ſide, we obſerved thereupon, was very preſſing upon us; <hi>I charge you by the roes and by the hindes of the field, that yee ſtirre-not-up nor awaken my Love untill ſhee pleaſe.</hi> The Note upon the ſide is (we doubt not but Interpretors give other Notes upon it; but this is for our uſe) Chriſt chargeth them, who have to doe in the Church, as it were by a ſolemne Oath, that they trouble not the quietneſſe thereof. And this wee thought fit to put as in the front and beginning of our buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118975:4"/>
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>VVEE have yet before wee come to our maine worke, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters to Preface before-you by way of Apologie for our Paſtour (ſuch he is to us, what ever he is to others) and for our moſt unworthy ſelves. And ſurely this is lawfull to be done, and more than expedient, it is neceſſary wee ſhould doe it. The glory of God and the Goſpell of His glorie, and the good of his poore people. All this and more then all is concerned in it. <hi>A Name</hi> ſaith the Wiſe, hee meanes a good name, a pretious name, for an ill name hath an ill ſavour, the Good doe, as wee may ſay, ſtop their noſes at it, not like the name of the wicked, but the very ſame, which <hi>rots above ground: A good name</hi> then is <hi>rather to be choſen then great Riches:</hi> and a very ſweet thing it is, and better then pretious oyntment; And being ſuch it deſerves to be kept ſo; and, what poſſible, to be kept as we doe our choyceſt things, in <hi>ſweets,</hi> all the yeare long. Now in doing this wee ſhall not ſweat to reſcue his name from off the tongues of wicked men, who ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good of evill, cannot poſſibly, but ſpeake evill of good. You know better than wee, what a good man ſaid (in common repute in thoſe dayes) hearing a bad man commend him, <hi>What evill have I done,</hi> ſaid he; It is poſſible, nay it was almoſt ordinary when time was, to heare the Devill himſelfe and his neareſt and deareſt ſervants ſpeaking excellent things of the Lords excellent ſervants, as of their Lord and Maſter himſelfe ſometimes: But then the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill hath a deſigne, ſo have his ſervants alſo. O it is a foule diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to the Good to heare the wicked ſpeake good of them. You remember that old preacher <hi>Bernard</hi> comming out of the pulpit and through the throng had the generall applauſe of the people (and generally they are ſtarke rotten, and ſtinking as is the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion that lyeth in the ditch, The good man went home weeping, and up to his cloſet pittifully mourning before his God; Lord, ſaid he, I have pleaſed the people to day and my ſelfe, which aſſureth mee, I have diſpleaſed Thee my God; whereas I ſhould rather diſpleaſe the whole world then Thee my God; ſo up to the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit againe the very next day, having ſcarce ſlept the night before, remembring the applauſe of the people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For you know what
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118975:4"/> followes; It is as good a ſigne of a good Miniſter as wee can rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily thinke of; Wicked men reproaching him, will not come at him; belch-out their ſpewing upon him, doe all they can againſt him, to thruſt him away. A good man ſure, and ſome good is done; The Devill is pinched; his ſervants rage; Now Gods work goes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; The Goſpel is on the thriving hand; It never gaines more than by oppoſition from the fleſh within, and the wicked without, <hi>contradicting</hi> and <hi>blaſpheming:</hi> That is excellent ſure the very <hi>wiſdome</hi> of God and <hi>power</hi> of God unto ſalvation, which the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned world with the rulers of the darkneſſe there, doe ſo mightily oppſe, contradict and blaſpheme: ſo now wee are careleſſe what the wicked ſay of our Miniſter, or of us, how can they ſpeake well, that are accuſtomed to doe ill? and make it their work all the day long, to take away the <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> of the <hi>righteous</hi> from him; Let them goe on; their night is comming, when they ſhall receive according to their meaſures, preſſed downe, running over (O that they could conſider!) It fares well with the Goſpell and all true Goſpellers: what care wee though we ſuffer a little: <hi>The Truth and the Church cannot be cruſhed no more then a Rooke can,</hi> ſaith our ſecond <hi>Rainolds:</hi> And ſith it is ſo, wee cannot be harmed.</p>
               <p>But now, though wee are as careleſſe as can be what the wicked ſay or what they doe, for they doe but after their kinde as thornes and briars and Scorpions uſe to doe. Yet doe we much regard what the godly-wiſe (amongſt theſe wee reckon your ſelfe) may thinke ſpeake or doe, in reference to him or them, who may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly be numbred with your ſelves, and accounted as they may have approoved themſelves, godly and wiſe alſo, for thus the caſe may be, and it is, as wee have cauſe to ſay, an ordinary caſe: Godly and wiſe men may entertaine prejudices and jealouſies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe, yea and take-up a report againſt them, and too rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily all this, and as groundleſly, eſpecially where there is not ſo ſweet an accord in point of judgement and practiſe betwixt them, as were to be wiſhed; and ſo it fals out too often, that where there is no cloſing in opinion (wee will call it but ſo) there is as little cloſing in affection with thoſe of a different opinion, and poſſibly muſt be ſo. And now let a report come, it is to the <hi>defaming</hi> of him or them, that differ from mee in judgement, I examine not the report or reporter, but, being to the deſaming of him that is not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118975:5"/> of the ſame minde with mee, how welcome is the report, and the reporter! the defamer and the defamation! Let nature ſpeak here for grace will be ſilent. And now, Deare Sir, we take leave to be more particular in theſe matters, being, as wee hinted hefore, of that high concernment, that wee may vindicate our Miniſter as we can, and put in a Caveat againſt that, which is ſo common wee would we could not ſay among the godly, <hi>raſh judging and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring</hi> before the time, when matters ſhould be well ſifted firſt, the party or parties heard, what they can ſay for themſelves. O it is good to heare all before wee judge any thing at all, elſe we may doe as prepoſterouſly as they did, who, as you finde it written, hanged a man in the forenoone, and enquired into his crime in the afternoone, whence <hi>Lidford</hi> law: and ſo wee, and worſe, if ſo wee doe, for judging the man before we have heard him, or how true that is, which is ſpoken of him, we may judge him, whom God accepteth; and in that which God alloweth, and commandeth; yet we lay a blot upon his name which haerebit will ſticke doe wee what wee can; And taint a man once in the opinion of the world, and he lyes open to any uſage; And ſo wee come to ſpeake for him, who hath ſpoken to God ſo much for us; and from God ſo much to us; that thereby wee may undeceive your ſelfe, and then wee ſhall with the ſame Labour undeceive others to the halfe of our pariſh and more, for you are the lazying or leading man, the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> very Biſhop amongſt us; <q>You have heard it objected againſt him, nay if it be not your owne objection, yet it is your jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, Godly we would call it, for ſo you have expreſſed your ſelfe once and againe, That whereas he ſhould deale in ſubſtantiall and fundamentall truths amongſt his people, he troubles them with matters of an inferiour nature, which might be forborne ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than ſpoken, and might wait their ſeaſon ſerving onely at preſent but to ingender ſtrife, and doubtfull diſputation, not tending at all to edification.</q>
               </p>
               <p>To this wee anſwer according to our knowledge, calling God to record upon our ſoules, as to the truth of that wee ſay, and wee doe appeale to the conſciences of every perſon that hath an eye heaven-ward, and applyed to him the eare, and is not a right <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio, that careth for none of thoſe things,</hi> whether he or they have or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily heard in our Country villages (for we hate compariſons)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118975:5"/> more pertinent texts choſen; more fully and with life followed, more feelingly preſſed, and all impertinences avoyded, as if it had been in the mans heart (and ſurely there it is for God put it there) to endeavour his utmoſt to declare unto us all the <hi>counſell of God,</hi> and ſo to keepe <hi>backe nothing</hi> that was <hi>proſitable to us.</hi> And this little is as much as we will ſay to that urged againſt him, his not inſiſting upon <hi>ſubſtantials;</hi> which yet had been in our judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, too much, had it not, as that alſo which followes, been forced, and, as wee may ſay, ſqeeſed from us; for <hi>Pudet hac oprobria nobis Et dici potuiſſe &amp; non potuiſſe refelli.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas it is further ſayd, That he deales in matters that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſtrife, and cauſe doubtfull diſputation; To this we could ſpeake as before, but certainly, Sir, It is as falſe as that <hi>Bubo</hi> is a Nightingale, to uſe our <hi>Jewel's</hi> words. Hee deale in matters ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring ſtrife! If we can poſſibly underſtand the Genius of the Man, hee abhorreth it with his heart. We cannot forget the time, when your neighbour-Miniſters, Learned and Godly indulged two dayes to thoſe horrid enemies &amp; adverſaries to Gods <hi>free grace</hi> through Chriſt, (which they make <hi>nature</hi> making it as common as <hi>nature,)</hi> and advancers of <hi>free will,</hi> that does more in order to the working<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our Salvation, then the ſupply of grace doth; and ſo Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill-man is ſet in a Throne, and the Lord of Glory (we ſhould tremble to ſpeake it, as you to heare it) on a Dung-hill that ſo theſe men of the earth might have advantage ground of Him, and call him, as ſome have don, <hi>ſatis pro imperio,</hi> to give an account of His matters: Wee were ſaying, Theſe proud men had two dayes for hearing what they could ſay, and ſo honoured they were by theſe Godly Miniſters, to diſpute it with them. We remember withall wee found our Miniſters ſpirit not a little ſtirred at this, knowing as he ſayd, That Truth would have no Glory by that Mouth-diſputation; for that theſe enemies having eſpouſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to theſe errours, will ſtand like the bound-ſtone, which you know had this Motto, <hi>Cedo nulli.</hi> And beſides they have a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous advantage againſt all good men, and the greater, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and wiſer they are, in the carrying on a diſpute with their tongues: for the Godly Learned and wiſe, have Faith and a good Conſcience, whereof they are as tender as of their eye; they are civill and modeſt withall, and cannot but deale as becometh God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118975:6"/> But theſe enemies have made Shipwrack of all—And you know what followes: Now this wee muſt not forget neither, That our Miniſter obſerving all this, for hee was preſent one day, and vvhat a Concourſe of people there were and ſome of his own charge, preſently after his returne, he choſe theſe Scriptures which vvee thinke it our duty to ſet downe, thereon to treat three or foure Lords dayes, <hi>Deut. 29. 29. Secret</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25. verſe: 4. <hi>The ſecret of</hi> &amp;c. <hi>John 17. 6. I have.</hi> Theſe Scriptures by divine aſſiſtance he ſo handled, That they vvhom God had inſtructed to diſcretion might clearely ſee, <hi>That Lambs may wade over thoſe Depths where Elephants muſt drowne;</hi> Hee deale in matters tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make ſtrife or cauſe doubtfull diſputation! No, he deales not in matters too high for him, and declines thoſe, as a Serpent in his vvay, that may cauſe ſtrife; therefore wee will ſay to this <hi>Cujus contrarium verum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Onely wee muſt appeale to your ſelfe, before vvee leave this matter; have not you ſaid more then once and lately twice in one day and before others, vvhich cauſed all this, That you have been urging him theſe three yeares almoſt, to diſpute with you, or to give you in vvriting the reaſons of his judgement and practiſe as to the matters of his God, and Diſcharge of his place, and yet you could not gaine ſo much at his hands: which tels you plainly, what naturally hee declines, and what mainely becometh him as every good Man to do, by doctrine to cleare his practiſe; and by practiſe to adorne his Doctrine; as grace may advance gifts, and gifts beautifie grace, this to his power hee hath done as one that <hi>ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes to be quiet,</hi> and to live-up to the <hi>Truth,</hi> rather then to diſpute it; for being clearely knowne to him, through Grace, to be the Truth as it is in Jeſus, Diſputation is but the Calling it into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, which is a debaſing of it, as to mixe Gold with Copper. Therefore till needs muſt he did forbeare; Therefore Sir, take your ſelfe for one witneſſe in this matter, and you are <hi>inſtar omnium,</hi> and beleive not what others ſay, who care not much what they ſay, That he intends not ſo much Edification, as to promote doubtfull diſputation; vvee ſay it againe, and wee ſay it clearely, It is a forged Cavillation, and a moſt falſe accuſation, for he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts it more then a fault, a Crime ſo to doe.</p>
               <p>But wee deſire not you ſhould truſt to what wee ſay; vve will <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:118975:6"/> take leave to proceed and make good what we ſay, holding it not impertinent to the matters in debate betwixt us; for, <hi>hinc illa la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thryma,</hi> the very riſe of all theſe clamours, <hi>Nec ad-huc finitus O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtes ſcriptus &amp; a tergo,</hi> Good Miniſters know full well what an evill people (ſuch vvee are all in the ſtate of nature) will require of them, <hi>Give out the Sacraments to them and hold-in the word, and they are ſatisfied;</hi> This he obſerved full well but tooke no notice; did as wee have heard a good Miniſter ſhould doe; hold on his courſe <hi>(Chryſoſtomes</hi> vvords) as the Moone in her Orbe, wholy careleſſe of, and neglecting the barkings and clamourings here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; and preſſed all along ſubſtantiall Truths, thereby to drive us out of our ſelves, and up to God; But when they would take no way, but the Sacraments they muſt have; he opened unto us the Doctrine of both the Sacraments; of Baptiſme, from <hi>Math: 28. 18, 19. Rom: 2. 28, 29. Gal: 3. 27. Col: 2. 11, 12.</hi> Of the Lords Supper, from 1 <hi>Cor: 10. 16. Matth: 26. 26. Mark. 14. 22, 23. Joh: 6. 50, 51,</hi> &amp;c. 63. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 11. 26. Surely it tendeth to our ſcope, thus to ſet them downe, vvhence matters were ſo handled, and with that cleareneſſe of Evidence, <hi>Who were to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Table of the Lord, and who not;</hi> that ſome were taken off from their eager purſuite that way; And others, the moſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing elſe left them, went on after their manner, Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting and blaſpheming. Now, vvhich muſt be added, though wee need not tell you vvhat was done in this place before, (for indeed vvee ſpare you, becauſe wee revereuce you) yet it is knowne all the Country over, vvhat is done in thoſe matters within a Mile and leſſe from this place, vvhere the Sacraments are given to him, and them, vvho are as ignorant as Ignorance it ſelfe, as rebellious as Rebellion it ſelfe—<hi>Et illud quod dicere nolo.</hi> Now then that Miniſters practiſe, is ſo contrary to the light ſhining forth from the Scriptures forementioned, after which, through Grace, our Miniſter orders every ſtep of his way; as that his way is as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that man's vvay (for we delight not to call him a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) as light is to darkneſſe, Chriſt to <hi>Beliall,</hi> the Temple of God to Idolls; Then what agreement betwixt theſe two, vvho ſtand as oppoſite, as to their judgement, at leaſt to their practiſe (for poſſible, <hi>video meliora)</hi> as doe the two Poles, North and South. Therefore it is ſtrange to us to heare it ſaid by you from him, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118975:7"/> wee beleive you, That our Miniſter returnes from him very well ſatisfied. It was anſwered before; be pleaſed to take this more; That our Miniſter can no more come downe to his practiſe, then a Mountaine can come downe and throw it ſelfe into the Sea, or the two Poles meet.</p>
               <p>Wee proceed to another thing which, as is ſaid, doth but cauſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſtrife, and ſerveth not to edifie; Now of this judge you by that vvhich followes.</p>
               <p>He obſerved, as vvho doth not, the <hi>Lords day</hi> preſumptuouſly ſleighted, and prophaned, and <hi>Chriſtmas-day</hi> highly honoured; now to ſhew the iniquity of this, he preached up the one, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt vvith the ſame breath he caſt downe the other. Be pleaſed to take his Scriptures here alſo, <hi>Gen: 2. 2. Exod. 20. 8. Iſa.</hi> 58. 13. and to lay his Batteryes againſt the other Idol-day, he choſe theſe Scriptures, <hi>Ioh:</hi> 4. 22. <hi>Gal:</hi> 4. 9, 10, 11, 12. This will fall to be one cheife part of our vvorke anon, and ſo wee leave it; Onely the reproaches caſt upon him for. this his Faithfullneſſe tohis Lord, puts us in mind of what wee have heard, <hi>That</hi> there was a good man accuſed for preaching a ſeditious Sermon, as was ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, but proofe failing, and not a word thorough the vvhole Sermon giving the leaſt evidence thereto, The accuſer ſpake open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and as impudently, <hi>If the Sermon was not, then the Text was ſeditious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the ſame is urged againſt him opening the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> vvhich though neceſſarily to be done, yet was he <hi>tantum non</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled thereunto, ſo unwilling, ſometimes, a man may be to doe his duty, yet being preſſed to give his reaſons for his not uſing of it, as others doe, he ſet upon it, and not ruſhing on it but after he had delivered the doctrine of Faith in a Catechiſticall way from ſeverall Scriptures, taking them much afterthe order, as they are in that, we commonly call, the <hi>Creed.</hi> And truly he gave ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why he ſaith not that prayer at the end of his; and why aGodly Miniſter ſhould not ſo doe; nor a godly man take it into his Cloſet, where he is ſeeking the face of his God, as that we are fully ſatisfied thereby, that ſo it ought not to be ſaid as common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and curſorily it uſeth to be; And withall, he gave us ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why a wicked man ought not to ſay that prayer at all, that we have concluded ever ſince we heard them, That a wicked man
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118975:7"/> hath no more to doe with the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> then he hath with the bleſſed Cup and body at the Lords Table; The one is as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely for his uncleane lips, as is the other for his filthy hands. But this will be the worke of the fourth Section.</p>
               <p>Now if it be asked by the way vvhat is all this to the preaching <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> of <hi>Chriſt Crucified,</hi> the preachers Text, and ſo he openeth the <q>whole <hi>Counſell of God?</hi> To this wee ſhall humbly reply, <hi>much every way:</hi> It is true nothing but Chriſt is to be preached unto Men as an object of their Faith, or as our learned <hi>Rainolds</hi> and holy <hi>Sibbes</hi> ſaith, <hi>a neceſſary Element of Salvation;</hi>
                  </q> Nothing but Chriſt Jeſus the Lord is the ſumme and Centre of all divine revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Truth: But there are other matters, which are to be preached, being reductive to Chriſt, and which meet in him. And whether thoſe things forementioned, 1. Relating to Admiſſion to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. 2. To His onely holy day; and 3. To His prayer, are not reductive to Chriſt, and meet in him, is left to the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Godly-wiſe. Thus farre as duty binde; us—more there is, but it is left to the Cloſet. He, as every good Man, in matters of this Nature, appeales to Gods judgement, and to that wee muſt ſtand, and wee ſhall doe well to minde thoſe Scriptures well, we reade <hi>Rom: 14. 4. &amp; 10. Who art thou</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and why doſt thou</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And ſo much for our Miniſter to vindicate him And give us <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> leave, we pray you, to Apologize a little, for this much wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt before the living God, the ſearcher of all hearts we have done it, very unwillingly; and have mooved as heavily here as is well Imaginable. But, Sir, you have compelled us from without, and our love to Chriſt, and the proſperity of his Goſpell, hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled us from within, knowing and fully aſſured, That nothing hath ſo obſtructed, the <hi>running</hi> thereof amongſt us, as have the Differences betwixt you two, The nearer the conjunction ſhould be, the more dangerous the diſcord is; wee may allude to it; for the <hi>Diviſions</hi> betwixt you, there are great thoughts of heart, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe that ſeeme godly, we hope they more then ſeeme: Now whence the riſe of theſe? or what hath cauſed them? The Lord be Judge, and help you to judge your ſelfe about it. He doth not doe as to ſacred adminiſtrations, as you did, why ſhould this Cauſe a Difference? You walked according to your light, ſo doth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118975:8"/> he according to his light; He cannot doe as you did, the word of his God, to his ſeeming, ſtanding like the Angel with a ſword in his way, and ſpeaking aloud unto him, if thou goeſt that broad way Ile ſlay thee; Why ſhould this make a difference? Would you have him ruſh upon the drawne ſword? God forbid. But you have ſaid he makes ſhrewde reflections upon you and your way: who can helpe that? But if ſo, which yet he knowes not of further then thus; The truth is <hi>Judex ſui &amp; obliqui,</hi> he hath done it moſt unwillingly: And you have it but by heare-ſay neither, and that is commonly a loude liar; and you muſt conſider your inſormers, whether enemies or friends to the Goſpell? Wee never heard you charge him but with that, wee humbly conceive, you ſhould have Commended him for: vvee muſt take leave to ſet it downe, becauſe that brought him upon the ſtage, where he at this time ſtands covered-over with as much filth as uncleane Mouthes, moſt naſty and filthy hands, and ſome pretty cleane too in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, can poſſibly caſt upon him. You muſt remember what you cannot forget, nor wee neither, the Towne and Country ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king notice of it, ſo viſible it was, being not done in a corner, when he preached firſt your Lecture at the Chappell neare him, we thought, and thinke ſo ſtill part of his charge, Not to mention the affronts againſt him at that time before he came to the Pulpit. His text you know was, <hi>Hoſ: 12. 10. I have alſo ſpoken by the Prophets,</hi>—having cleared the knowne Doctrine of the text, and grounded it, and comming to make Application of it, A Conſecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry two or three he preſſed firſt; and this for one, <hi>That the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Chriſt, being the Mouth of Chriſt, and ſtanding in his ſtead, muſt ſpeake and doe in the matters of Chriſt, as the Lord Chriſt would ſpeake and doe, if he were here upon Earth.</hi> You know and wee know, he ſpent but few Minutes upon this, indeed he ſpake feelingly (as one that felt the weight of his charge) and ſmartly, and was there not a cauſe? being in his owne place, and knowing full well the horrid doings there? Sir, wee make bold to tell you, and in as much love as you can conceive is due to you from us; had your <hi>force</hi> been right, and your way good, and not complying too much with the Miniſters way of that Chappell. You had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended our Miniſter, given him the right hand of fellowſhip, and taken him at that time into your boſome. But what agreement?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118975:8"/> when your wayes lie ſo croſſe (which will appeare, we conceive, through-out the following diſcourſes) to the way of Holineſſe, you and we are charged to walke-in. Till you ſhall take this into your thoughts, and <hi>muſe</hi> upon it, things will be, as they are, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on headlong to the great diſhonour of God, reproach of His Word, and ſcandall of His people, as we ſuppoſe: for the cloſe of this, in much love we entreate you to examine what an affront was put upon the <hi>Word,</hi> when at your earneſt requeſt our Paſtour tooke a turne in that Lecture, you know when and where, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine we pray you, what the man did you commonly call the <hi>Clerke,</hi> but might as truely call a <hi>Beaſt,</hi> If he turne his backe upon the Word, as he more than ſeemed ſo to doe then, going forth of the place, as others did, at the time when the ſaid Miniſter went up into the pulpit. And upon your examination of the matter, we know what is your duty to doe, if you will doe it. For Sir (it is our perſwaſion) did your Brethren, whom we honour, we thinke, as much as you doe, underſtand well and thorowly how matters are carried there, how unbecoming the Goſpell, and croſſe to the proſperity of the ſame, they would have things cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, or they would not, we thinke they ſhould not, unleſſe they be of your perſwaſion, take their turne there. Looke to it, Sir, and be perſwaded, that for the Glory of God and our Deare Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and that His Goſpell may <hi>run</hi> and <hi>be glorified,</hi> and that you may correct what is amiſſe, and have peace at the Laſt, have we ſpoke hitherto, and ſhall ſpeake, for, God forbid, we ſhould be ſilent in ſuch matters as theſe, being called upon to ſpeake and give our opinion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>IN the next place we come to ſpeake a little for our ſelves, our matters ſo requiring, yea conſtraining; for we are as unwilling to doe it as you can thinke us, in ſome reſpects; but, in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, moſt willing. Wee are, Sir, and you know it, and wee bleſſe God from our hearts, He hath made us know it too, moſt unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ones. Truely Sir, our inward thoughts are (all thoughts are inward, but theſe are cloſeſt unto us, and moſt fixed there) that we are ſuch unworthy ones, in and of our ſelves confidered, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118975:9"/> we cannot thinke we have thought our ſelves <hi>low enough,</hi> till we have thought our ſelves to <hi>nothing,</hi> yea worſe <hi>than nothing,</hi> as in our ſelves ſtill; and if ſuch <hi>nothings</hi> now, now that He hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>to reveale His Son in us,</hi> to plucke us out of our blood, to waſh us thorowly, and ſo to <hi>ſloud it away,</hi> looking upon us and accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of us in Him, in Whom to be accepted is our Labour, our am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, the topp of our glory, and crowne of rejoycing; we were ſaying, If ſuch <hi>Nothings</hi> now, what were we then, when we <hi>lay-in Evill,</hi> like a Carrion in the Ditch, but more corrupted and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting: being under the power of a luſt within, and that <hi>wicked one</hi> without; What were we then better than others? Children of wrath ſo ſoone as we were the Children of men. And had not Grace withheld us, and an All-mighty-Hand raighned us-in, we had been as mad with rage againſt the Saints, and ſtood as croſſe to their <hi>way of Holineſſe,</hi> as once <hi>Paul</hi> was, before he came to his <hi>right mind;</hi> And in every myre of ſin, we could have reached un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, we had wallowed with great delight, as a ſwine doth, and as they now doe, who lye with the <hi>world in wickedneſſe,</hi> for thither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our will hurried-us, driving us as faſt from God, as doth the moſt impetuous ſtreame run from its fountaine. And all this while (pertaking, by priviledge of our Infant Baptiſme, of all Goſpell Communions) we ſhould have thought our condition unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably bleſſed, taking <hi>Sanctuary</hi> under the <hi>ſhaddow</hi> of a <hi>Church,</hi> whoſe height, like that <hi>Tree, reacheth unto heaven, and the ſight thereof to the end of all the Earth.</hi> But He, from Whom wee were running, by His Spirit in His Word laid-hold-on us, <hi>and ſo being mercifull to us,</hi> delivered us out of our own hands, and from our ſelves, as <hi>Lot out of Sodom</hi> (the greateſt Enemies to our ſoules we know in the world, the <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Spirit</hi> of the world not excepted) and gave us an and gave us an hand of faith, whereby we laid hold on Him; And now He vvill hold us faſt, and give us power to hold Him, and to vvalke <hi>in all pleaſing</hi> before Him. And now, vvhat ſhall we ſay? <hi>Even ſo Father, becauſe it pleaſed Thee;</hi> Who at firſt ſpake <hi>light out of Darkneſſe,</hi> and <hi>cauſed it to ſhine into our hearts,</hi> even <hi>the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> The thoughts of this comming ſtrongly upon us at the time vvhen wee vvere ſeeking His face, engaged us, being ſo preſſed unto it from vvithout, to give an account of the Truth of the <hi>way,</hi> our <hi>walke</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:118975:9"/> and practiſe in it. And ſo having beleived, we ſhall ſpeake. This then was the prime and chief prevailing motive to make further enquiry into theſe things, and to give our experiences about them, as we are perſwaded duty bindeth us, and our engagement is to doe, for</p>
               <p>If theſe things be ſo, as even now we have ſpoken; and the Lord God hath laid His hand upon us, and by His Finger His Holy Spirit, written the <hi>Law of our Relation upon our hearts,</hi> as He <note place="margin">Upon Gal. 2. 20. pag. 36.</note> ſtandeth to us, and we to Him in Jeſus Chriſt [we borrow this expreſſion from that Man of God M <hi>Bridge,</hi> who to us, ſpake much in that little; and ſurely it containeth much, and we have made, through Grace, much of it, as may appeare throughout our ſeventh and laſt Section) Not doubting but whoſoever ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire at <hi>that Law of Relation,</hi> what is to be done, as to Church. Adminiſtrations, ſhall have full reſolution therefrom, and ſo <hi>end the matter:</hi> Therefore here we ſhall be very briefe, making men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it onely in Reference to our ſelves, our <hi>way,</hi> and <hi>walke,</hi> and this we were ſaying] If the Lord hath don thus with us, as having beleived, we have ſpoken, then we humbly conceive theſe things muſt follow.</p>
               <p n="1">1. We muſt <hi>follow</hi> the Lord <hi>fully,</hi> as <hi>deare children,</hi> by the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Holy Spirit of Faith and Adoption, which the Sons of God have, <hi>another</hi> from that of the world, which rules in the darkneſſe thereof. We muſt walke by <hi>rule,</hi> even as <hi>He walked.</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 6. <hi>If children of the light we walke in the light, even as He is in the light,</hi> 1 John 1. 7. Elſe (1) we ſhould cleane croſſe the end of our <hi>Election, choſen in Him that we ſhould be Holy, and without Blame before Him in Love,</hi> Eph: 1. 4. And (2) wee ſhould elſe croſſe the end of our <hi>Calling; As He who hath called you is holy, ſo be ye Holy in all manner of Converſation,</hi> 1 Pet: 1 15. 2. 9. And (3) we ſhould elſe croſſe the end of Gods Diſcovering to us His Goſpell and way of Holineſſe, It was that we ſhould walke thereafter, having a Converſation as becometh, <hi>Phil:</hi> 1. 27. leaſt our unholy practiſe ſhould give our holy profeſſion the lye—but we haſten.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If we can ſay, <hi>Truly our fellowſhip is with ths Father, and with His Son Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Joh: 1. 3. Aſſuredly then we can not but ſeeke after, and bend towards a Communion and fellow
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118975:10"/> ſhip one with another, that we may watch over each other; help to beare each others burthen; ſupply each others wants; pertake of each others Graces; doe all things as becommeth a Communion of Saints on earch (which is ſaith that Learned Man, <note place="margin">Upon Job 16. pag. 25 4.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lower heaven of the Saints)</hi> ſerving each other in Love; For thus wee have concluded, That as it is with <hi>lines in a Circumſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> the nearer to their <hi>Center,</hi> the nearer one to another; So nearneſſe to Chriſt cannot poſſibly conſiſt with a ſtrangereſſe or diſtance one from another, for wee are members one of another.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>If, as He is ſo are we in this world,</hi> 1 Joh: 4. 17. That is, as we have heard it expounded: If we have His image in us, and ſtamped upon us, if His Love <hi>be ſhed abroad in our hearts;</hi> If He be in us by His Bleſſed Spirit; we in Him by our faith; If he dwell in us, and walke in us, 2 <hi>Cor: 6. 16. Then ought we to walke even as He walked,</hi> which was ſaid before: But from hence we humbly conceive theſe two things will follow.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Wee muſt <hi>come out from among them,</hi> and be <hi>ſeperate from the world</hi> ſo farre as is poſſible, and not goe <hi>out of the world, 1 Cor:</hi> 5. 10. in all times and places, ſpecially at the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; for ſo ſaith the Lord, <hi>Be ye ſeperate and touch not the uncleane thing,</hi> if ye expect that I ſhould <hi>receive you, and be a Father unto you, and ye Sons and Daughters unto Mee,</hi> 2 Cor: 6. 17. Surely they that walke with God as friends, cannot walke with the world, be companions with the men thereof <hi>upon choice,</hi> their affaires not requiring, and when they plainly ſee, they can give no good unto them. But if they could have the leaſt hope, they could by converſing with them, communicate good unto them, they would moſt willingly doe it; yet then not as <hi>companions</hi> with them, but <hi>Phyſitians</hi> to them; <hi>for what fellowſhip hath righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with unrighteouſneſſe? what Communion hath light with dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? and what concord hath Chriſt with Beliall?</hi> And</p>
               <p n="2">2. Wee muſt meet often in ſome place, beſides the common meeting place, elſe how can <hi>we ſpeake often one to another?</hi> ſo making full proofe <hi>that we feare the Lord,</hi> Mal: 3. 16. Surely it is cleare from that place, That that was the manner and practiſe of the Saints of old. And M. <hi>Rogers</hi> in his fift Treatiſe <hi>pag:</hi> 109. gives us a famous Inſtance of ſome brethren with their Paſtour
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118975:10"/> that met together in the yeare 1588. privately in one houſe, there to complaine to each other of their ſinnes and wants; and to finde out the remedies againſt the ſame. That holy man in the ſame place, gives us to know the good of that Conference, which he brancheth forth into many perticulars, if we well remember, but we finde them contracted into three.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This meeting was a great whetting-on to them to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the publique Miniſtery more carefully, and fruitfully after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Theſe two kinds of meetings, publickly in the Church and privately in their houſes thus carried, did knit them together in that bond of brotherly love, which, during life, could never be broken.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It was a meanes to make them have Chriſtian conference and godly communion in greater account.</p>
               <p>Wee vvill take leave to adde hereunto that holy Man's words, <note place="margin">Mr. Tilling: Serman, p 200.</note> now with Him, <hi>whoſe he was,</hi> and <hi>whom he ſerved. The reaſon why there is ſo little of the Spirit given forth, though it be the great</hi> New Teſtament promiſe, <hi>is this, Becauſe Saints are no more in aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling together. Saints are not found, as they ſhould be, in their worke of Aſſembling together; When the Lord Chriſt gave His Spirit to His Apoſtles immediately at His Reſurrection, it was when they were aſſembled together,</hi> Joh: 20. 19. 22. <hi>When the Diſciples were aſſembled together He breathed on them,</hi> and ſaid unto them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>And ſo we reade in the</hi> 2 Acts; <hi>where wee have the more full giving-forth of the Spirit, It was when the Saints were aſſembled togetehr, when</hi> they were all with one accord in one place; <hi>He might have given it to them one by one, when they were alone: But our Deare Lord chooſeth to give-forth the Spirit, when they were Aſſembled together: To aſſure us how much He loveth the Aſſemblies of the Saints; He will not give to every one in a corner alone, but when aſſembled together: So that if Saints neglect their meeting together, there may be little enjoyment of the Spirit, though it be the great promiſe of the New Teſtament Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is much more to be ſaid for this meeting together of the Saints, and there is much ſaid againſt it, vvee ſhall referre both this and that to another place, the laſt Section.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:118975:11"/>
               <p>2. Wee proceed to remove an offence taken againſt us, we ſay taken, for God knowes, we know not when and wherein any was given. Thus it is ſuggeſted, That we are regardleſſe of others, who walke not in fellowſhip with us. Much more is ſaid, but we ſhall heare more of it in another place; This we will ſay here firſt.</p>
               <p>1. That no good man can be regardleſſe of another how bad ſoever; nay the worſe he is, the more regard a good man hath unto him, ſo as he could take ſuch an one into his boſome, ſo be thereby he could make him better. 2. Wee profeſſe from our hearts, <hi>now that wiſdome hath entred-in thither, and knowledge is pleaſant to our ſoule.</hi> That we cannot but love all we have the leaſt hope, <hi>doe love the Lord Jeſus in ſincerity,</hi> obſerving their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly walke according to the rule of the Word and Commands of the Goſpell, under what formes or Notions ſoever they be; that is little or nothing to us, they <hi>love the Lord in ſincerity,</hi> and that is motive enough, and bond ſtrong enough upon us to love them. That <hi>Chriſt hath received us,</hi> prevailes much <hi>to receive one another.</hi> Though yet we confeſſe, we cannot but invite others to come-in and joyne with us, (we know He is the Lord, that <hi>perſwades</hi> to come-in <hi>and adds to the Church)</hi> but we ſay, we cannot but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite others to come-in to us, and walke along with us; Aſſuring them that they ſhall finde the ſame that we doe, <hi>That all the wayes of wiſdome are wayes of pleaſantneſſe, and all her pathes are peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. And yet, That they may not be too haſty, and ſo rather ſtumble into the way, than take into it upon choice, we doe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe them to ſit downe firſt and count their coſt: Aſſuring them from as ſure a word as the Heaven and Earth have for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing, that they muſt come off from their <hi>owne way,</hi> a way of ſinne and death, and caſt a <hi>ſpewing</hi> upon it, that they may no more returne unto it, than they would to their vomit to take it up againe, before they can enter this way to walke in it as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth with a right foote, in <hi>all pleaſing,</hi> as before Him, Who hath called us <hi>out of darkneſſe</hi> into <hi>His marvailous light:</hi> Wee tell them moreover, leaſt they, finding themſelves miſtaken, ſhould returne backe to their <hi>Egypt</hi> of ſinne and Darkneſſe, That though it be as pleaſant a way as pleaſantneſſe it ſelfe, yet, ſo <hi>ſaith the Spirit,</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118975:11"/> renewed, not, ſo ſaith the fleſh; for not one ſtepp ſcarce is taken therein, but it goes to the heart of fleſh and blood. And truly to take it in paſſage, hereby wee conclude the truth of our way; That it is <hi>the way of holineſſe,</hi> which is a <hi>torment</hi> to fleſh, not mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, as fleſh is a torment to it. And ſo we ſay farther to him or her, that beares any liking to this way, and makes ſome offers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it (wee give all encouragement that can be (for who dares deſpiſe the day of <hi>ſmall things,</hi> the leaſt motions or breathings heaven-ward how welcome!) yet wee ſay further, and it is good to tell them the worſt with the beſt; That they never found what a <hi>rebell</hi> fleſh was till now; nor a <hi>buſie Devill</hi> till now; nor what perſecution is till now; which if they meet not with from without (and that were a wonder, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Odium genius evangehj.</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred is the companion and very ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius of the Goſpel. 2 Tim. 3. 12.</note> Hell-gates ſtanding wide open againſt them night and day) yet certainly they ſhall meet with from within; for ſo ſaith the Spirit by the Miniſtery thereof, <hi>All that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus ſhall ſuffer perſecution;</hi> and wee have our Maſters word for it, <hi>In the world yee ſhall have tribulation;</hi> 
                  <q>which word though, hath not the leaſt power or efficacy in it ſelfe, but onely as it is managed in the hand of Satan, to turne Men from God; And yet the Lord Chriſt hath not let that goe free without its deadly wound, but bids his followers be of <hi>good comfort, for He hath overcome the world,</hi> that is, for them and in their ſtead; ſo that it ſhould never be uſed nor heightned in its enmity to a totall and finall conqueſt over them;</q> theſe are the words of that Godly and learned Man Dr <hi>O wen:</hi> But this is the <note place="margin">Saints perſev: p. 170.</note> point which wee would drive-on like a naile to the head, and preſſe upon our ſelves and others, <hi>Circumſpect walking, ſelfe-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall every day,</hi> yea every houre in the day, <hi>looking off</hi> from all that is fleſh, and up to Him who is the <hi>Alpha,</hi> and will be the <hi>Omega,</hi> the Author and finiſher of <hi>our faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. And now that God hath thus perſwaded with us by his <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> and <hi>Word,</hi> wee doe after the manner of his people in all ages, (which was hinted before) who feared their God, <hi>ſpake often one</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 3. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>unto another;</hi> and wee feele the comfort of it; And blame our ſelves moſt for not doing it ſooner; but bleſſed be God wee doe it now, and that he hath given us ſuch a Paſtour, who deſires to know the <hi>ſtate of his flocke,</hi> that they may be made meet in Gods time to give him the meeting at his Table; Truly we bleſſed God
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118975:12"/> for this day and night, and ſome of us for this great mercy, that we never were at the Lords Table, for had wee taken the invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being ſixteene yeares of age, as multitudes did doe, we had done wee know not what, as others did, and our Miniſter at that time had given it to He knew not whom: For how could the Miniſter poſſibly know our ſtate, who never, to our remembrance, met with us, but at a merry-meeting, or the day before wee were to meet at the Lords Table, and then he that gave us the Queſtion made us the Anſwer—We paſſe over this, and through the ſtrength of grace, paſſe on in this way, aſſembling of our ſelves together, as our Callings will give leave, for the mutuall edification each of other, and wee doubt not but ere long all the Miniſters of the Lord, that are truly godly, what ever they doe at preſent, walking according to their light, will draw-on their people this vvay; and be as often with them in private, as in the publique place; minding with all their hearts the danger of the neglect thereof, either in Miniſter, or in people; vvhere the Apoſtle layes that riſe of that ſoul-damning-ſinne of wilfull Apoſtacy in the neglect of this, <hi>Heb. 10 25. Not forſaking the Aſſembling of our ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is, but exhorting one another,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For if we ſinne wilfully,</hi> verſe 26.</p>
               <p>5. Wee have now given you at your requeſt ſome account of our vvay; vvee ſhall point you now in paſſage, vvhat lets and rubs we finde in the way (it vvere not elſe the way of Holineſſe, for the broad way meets with none.) And the way vvee take thorough grace to paſſe over them, with much cheare and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in our ſpirits being reſolved upon the vvay, and aſſured what vvee muſt meet with walking therein.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a way much reproached (wee like it ſo much the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for that) <hi>That old liar</hi> and <hi>Murtherer</hi> with his ſervants are ſtill caſting a flood upon it, vvhich they will never doe upon their owne way of ſinne and death, yet that is one let and a great rub to fleſh and blood. And</p>
               <p n="2">2. This is another, becauſe many of that vvay vvalke not ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly in it as were to be wiſhed, and vvee have fleſh as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and carry the ſame <hi>Dung-hill,</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> about us as the vvorſt of men doe (yet with this difference, for wee muſt not vvrong our ſelves, much leſſe the worke of his grace in us) this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118975:12"/> 
                  <hi>Dun-hill</hi> ſavoureth like a dung-hill in our noſtrils, the filthieſt ſinke that is in the world; but with a wicked man like a garden of ſpices; ſo our heart is an <hi>Hell</hi> too, and an Hell to us, whereas to a vvicked man it is an heaven, becauſe it iſſueth forth to him the way and meanes, firſt wrought and moulded within, whereby to reach at, and, if poſſible, to attaine all the ſweets of profits and pleaſures here below) but as vvee were ſaying, becauſe we have this <hi>Dung-hill,</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> within us, which is ſtill putting forth from us, and wee have many eyes upon us to obſerve our walking, wee are carefull with all our care that wee may cut off all occaſions, that the way of Holineſſe may not be blaſphemed through us; for though wee doe meet once a weeke, yet ſo as it doth not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der but further our private affaires, as wee have found by good experiences, and indeed ſo much profit every way, ſpecially to our <hi>inward man (though Piety is proſperity</hi> enough where ever it is, and <hi>Impiety miſery enough where ever that is, the hid man of the heart is the all of man,</hi> ſo be that proſpers all proſpers, for ſeldome or never without abundance of grace doth the outward and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward proſper together) we were ſaying, That wee are, through the grace of God ſuch gainers, by attending the meanes of grace, that wee would not for a world neglect the aſſembling of our ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is, but <hi>hold-on, exhorting one the other,</hi> and ſo much the more as wee ſee the day <hi>approaching;</hi> for this was ſpoken once and we heard it twice; <hi>That they who will have nothing of the Sabbath on the weeke day, will take-in much of the weeke on the Sabbath day, if not all:</hi> The meaning is plaine to them that will underſtand.</p>
               <p>6. But now to cut off occaſion, wee walke in deſire and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour orderly and as becometh the Goſpell, wee meddle not with things too high for us, wee are not Intruders into the ſacred Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and utterly diſlike thoſe that are; wee take counſell at Gods mouth, and of his Miniſters; wee pray and exhort one another much in thoſe words; <hi>Onely let your converſation be as becometh</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>the Goſpell of Chriſt.</hi> And then wee depart home, and finde no want of our abſence there, according to the good word of our Lord wee finde it hath been with us, <hi>other things have been added to us;</hi> As our Lord knew our needs were. Wee take it for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, our Maſter in Heaven, is the beſt Maſter, and gives the beſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118975:13"/> reward to his ſervants, for He Himſelfe and not another for Him will be <hi>their reward:</hi> So will He be their <hi>Defence</hi> alſo, nothing ſhall hurt them, or be dammage to them, while they are attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing His ſervice.</p>
               <p>Wee will inſiſt upon this a little, that we may give, if not ſome ſatisfaction, yet ſome anſwer to thoſe that ſay, <hi>Is is enough and as</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 2. <hi>Nempe quod ad carnis prudenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am attinet.</hi> Bez. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>much as is required to attend Gods ſervice on the ſtated-Day in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> and <hi>an houre out of ſeaſon</hi> (as the wiſdom of the fleſh calls it) <hi>would be no ſmall loſſe or hinderance to them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. To this we would humbly reply. 1. That this being ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely charged upon the Miniſter to preach the Word; <hi>to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon,</hi> it reacheth the hearers alſo; If there muſt be preaching, there muſt be hearing, and there muſt be ſome time of conferring together about what was heard, and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Miniſters <hi>ſayings,</hi> as thoſe wiſe hearers did, <hi>Acts</hi> 17 11. with the <hi>ſayings</hi> of God, and what profit came of it, all which cannot be, as we conceive, <hi>but by ſpeaking often one to another.</hi> And for that ſuppoſed dammage, That an houre or two in a weeke would cauſe unto the outward man; it is but caſt-in by the <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reaſon</hi> of thoſe that <hi>minde earthly thengs.</hi> It is an unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Truth, The fleſh never complaineth of the <hi>waſte</hi> or loſſe of time, while it is pleaſed; but every houre is two, while that is vexed and <hi>put to coſt;</hi> yet wee may be reſolved at this point, <hi>While the Soule is a gainer, the man is no looſer;</hi> and, <hi>while the ſoule is a looſer, the man is no gainer. Spirituall accommodations will make a good heart forget temporall incommodities:</hi> It is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy our beſt obſervation, as that worthy Man hath it, what a full <note place="margin">Upon <hi>Job 6. 6. p. 441. Ch:</hi> 22. 21.</note> compenſation the Lord makes to His people, for the want of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall bread and water: <hi>Though ye are cut ſhort in outward things, yet ye ſhall not be ſhortned in Spiritualls; The raine of the holy Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine ſhall not be removed from you,</hi> which we tranſlate, <hi>Thy Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers ſhall not be removed,</hi> Iſai. 30. 20. Joel 2. 23. Surely they that looke <hi>Sion-</hi>ward finde much in this, to engage them to heare much, and to conferre about that they heare, and to take time for it, what poſſibly can be ſpared from their worldly employments, which muſt be ſerved in their ſeaſon, yet ſo as greater matters of infinite concernment be not neglected.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:118975:13"/>2. In the ſecond place we could take the boldneſſe here, To entreate the people of God to ſpeake their experiences, whether they have not found as gratious an hand with them, and as ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular a providence over them attending Gods ſervice at conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent times, as once the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God did, while they are ſo well employed according to their Lords command, <hi>The enemy ſhall not exact upon them nor the Son of wickedneſſe afflict them;</hi> What a ſweet and heart-chearing providence was it, That when all the <hi>Males</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> appeared <hi>thrice in the yeare</hi> before the Lord at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> none of their Neighbour Nations (though profeſſed enemies to <hi>Iſraell;</hi> on the <hi>Eaſt</hi> the <hi>Ammonites</hi> and <hi>Moabites;</hi> on the Weſt the <hi>Philiſtines;</hi> on the South the <hi>Egyptians</hi> and <hi>Idumaeans;</hi> and on the North the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> ſhould ſo much <hi>as deſire their Land,</hi> Exod: 34. 24. Such a fatherlike care their God had over them, while they tooke care of Duty, That He not onely <hi>ſtopped hands from ſpoiling,</hi> but <hi>hearts from deſiring.</hi> Againe, it was as ſweet a providence as it was wonderfull, That after the ſlaughter of <hi>Gedaliah</hi> ſo pleaſant a Country, (left utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtitute of Inhabitants, and compaſſed about with ſuch war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Nations, as were the <hi>Ammonites, Moabites, Edomites, Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines)</hi> was not invaded, nor replanted by forraighners for ſeventy yeares ſpace, but the roome kept empty; till the returne of the Naturalls: Surely looke what the <hi>Spirit</hi> ſpake to the Angell of the Church in <hi>Philadelpha,</hi> there <hi>He ſpake unto us: Becauſe thou haſt kept the word of my patience, I alſo will keepe thee from the houre of temptation, which ſhall come upon all the world to trie them that dwell upon the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. In the laſt place to ſtop the mouth of carnall reaſon, That enemy and adverſary of all righteouſneſſe, and let alone, will have all the talke, though, in the iſſue, it will prove to be but contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting and blaſpheming, the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>His Grace,</hi> the <hi>way</hi> and <hi>practiſe</hi> of <hi>His holy Ones;</hi> This we ſay to him, who accounts that time runs-out to waſte, which is taken up in holy conference, about what hath been heard, and what profit they have received thereby, That this man hath never heard to purpoſe, the Word hath not been prevaling with him to Converſion; for, if ſo, The recalling of it, and meditation upon it had been ſweet unto him,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118975:14"/> and he would obſerve time and place, as he doth often alone by himſelfe; ſo alſo ſometimes, as his affaires may give leave, among others alſo, to tell his experiences that way, what furthered or hindred in that worke, of profiting by hearing, that ſo he may promote the good of others, as his owne; for how deſirous is he, <hi>That all were as he is,</hi> excepting his reproaches and ſcornes for the Name of Chriſt; <hi>Holding forth the word of life; He, that is rich enough (in grace) is nothing worth,</hi> and he, that ſayes, he hath enough of the Word, hath none at all to purpoſe, or to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by it. <hi>Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you richly in all wiſdome, Col:</hi> 3. 6. We we about to ſet downe a little of that much <hi>Zanche</hi> hath upon thoſe words, but wee intend to be ſhort, wee will onely heare what Holy <hi>Sibs</hi> ſpeaks to this matter. <q>They that are acquainted with their owne wants, thinke it an happineſſe to have plenty; and they that know their naturall weakneſſe, know they need all ſpirituall ſupports and helps to keepe the veſſell of their Soules in perpetuall good caſe. They know alſo, that the more they know, as <hi>they ought to know,</hi> in deſire and endeavour, living-up to what they know, the fitter they are for doing and ſuffering; for communion with God, and for all paſſages both of life and death, therefore they cannot have too much care this way.</q>
               </p>
               <p>7. One thing more wee would adde for the clearing of our practiſe, and removing an offence (not given, we hope, but ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt us) That wee attend the publike place of hearing with all care and attention, and our private exerciſe at home, and at our private meeting place with all Diligence, ordering matters ſo, by the help of Grace, that th'one hinder not, but further the other. Some are all for reading and praying at home, For they have good bookes there to reade and pray-by both: Others againe are all at the publike, and nothing at home. To this onely this may ſuffice, That the uſe of the private exerciſes with the neglect and contempt of the publique, have a <hi>curſe</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them: And the uſe of the publique, with the neglect and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the private, have the ſame <hi>curſe</hi> too: for both th'one and the other are indeed not uſed but abuſed.</p>
               <p>8. Thus we have given you an account of the <hi>way</hi> the Lord
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118975:14"/> hath been pleaſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o draw us unto by His good Word and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and to fix our foot-in; how alſo wee have paſſed-over the offences, have been given to us in our way; and removed, as we could, thoſe, that have been taken againſt us; more we have to ſay, but we referre it to another place; yet this we cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to ſay, That wee finde this way ſo pleaſant and good, <hi>ſo ſaith the Spirit</hi> (the fleſh is a flug, an enemy rather) and ſo ſaith nothing, or elſe contradicteth and blaſphemeth, or would doe ſo, were it let alone to doe what it would) but ſo pleaſant it is, and ſo ſaith the Spirit; That wee would not for a world be in the way, in the dayes of our ignorance we were-in; And wee wiſh from our hearts ſo well we wiſh you, That you were in the ſame way too, though it be as neglected and reproached a <hi>way</hi> as the <hi>Church</hi> her ſelfe is, <hi>This is Zion which no man ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after.</hi> A <hi>ſure way-Mark it is</hi> that it is the right way, cleane croſſe to the way of the world, where fleſh and blood finds <hi>Rehoboth</hi> roomth enough, nothing to croſſe it, or to put it to Coſt, therefore <hi>right in every mans own eyes, though it be the way to hell, going downe to the Chambers of death</hi> But <hi>Zions way,</hi> or the way to <hi>Zion</hi> lyeth ſo croſſe to fleſh, that it can as well chooſe to walke upon burning coales, as, upon choice, to walke in this <hi>way,</hi> till it be mortifyed. The ſerious thoughts of this put us firſt to a ſtand, cauſed us to looke round about us, and conſider in what way our foot ſtood, To put it to Queſtion, and not take reſolution from fleſh and blood, <hi>Is our way Right?</hi> (for indeed, Sir, wee were, we will not ſay in the ſame way with you, but in the way of the world we were, while wee lay with the world in wickedneſſe) Is our way right in our Lord's eyes? <hi>For every way of man is,</hi> as we reade, <hi>right in his owne eyes,</hi> Prov: 21. 2. but that way is an abomination to the Lord. Indeed thus through Grace, we reaſonedupon the <hi>way,</hi> and ſaw clearely, the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercifull to us, and anoynting our eyes <hi>with His eye-ſalve,</hi> That the way ſo <hi>right in our owne eyes, was our owne way,</hi> a way of ſin and death, very pleaſing to fleſh, putting it to <hi>no coſt,</hi> none at All, therefore infinitely diſpleaſing to God. And ſo we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, That they have a very difficult worke, if not a deſperate cauſe in their hand, who would maintaine, <hi>That way right in a</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:118975:15"/> 
                  <hi>man's owne eyes,</hi> to be the way of Gods Holy ones, with whom He walkes and they with Him, <hi>circumſpectly</hi> ſure, according to their charge in deſire and endeavour <hi>exactly</hi> full up to the rule—But we muſt contract, we have told what firſt put us to a ſtand, and enquire for <hi>the old-way,</hi> that <hi>good way,</hi> paved forth as a <hi>Cauſey-way,</hi> and traced by the footſteps of the Lord's A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted.</p>
               <p>2. This moved with us very much to haſten out of that way of the world, ſo right in its owne eyes, and ſtirred-up our Spirits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it as much almoſt, (for we want his zeale,) not altogether as <hi>Paul</hi> was ſtirred, when he beheld thoſe abominable Idolaters; And as <hi>Luther</hi> was ſtirred in his Spirit againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> obſerving the <hi>Popes giving pardons for we know not how many yeares;</hi> Indeed we have heard, that gave the firſt offence to that <hi>Gideon</hi> of our times, or but a Century of yeares by-paſt. And how did he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirre himſelfe after that time (take it in paſſage and make uſe of it) to render Popery (that <hi>rode-way</hi> of the world, or Nationall Church there right in its owne eyes) ſo corrupt and ſtinking as any Carrion can be in the Noſtrills of every man, that hath but the uſe of ordinary reaſon, ſo full of folly and Blaſphemy it is? We were ſaying that this moved with us very much to haſten-out of that way of the world, to wit, <hi>The obſervation we made by our eye and eare of thoſe abominable uſeages,</hi> thoſe prophane mixtures in <hi>Gods-houſe,</hi> we meane the meeting place for God's people, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and countenanced by the Stewards there. Why? no man ſo uncleane though he wallowes like a ſwine in all the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Myres and filths of the world (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 20.) yet cleane e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough being a <hi>waſhed ſwine,</hi> we meane, upon account, of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Baptiſme, to be a welcomed gheſt unto the Lord's Table. Once more, Why? No man ſo bad, though worſe than any Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell, a jearer, a ſcoffer, a ſcorner, that ſets <hi>a City on a flame,</hi> that will doe unjuſtly for an half-peny-gaine, when a heathen would not doe it for leſſe than a kingdome; A man that declares his ſin like <hi>Sodome, he hides it not</hi> why yet he was Baptized, and is a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed ſwine, and upon that ſcore he muſt be admitted, as a worthy gueſt to the Lord's Table; So ſoone as we were enabled through grace, to make obſervation of theſe Doings in Gods-Houſe, wee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118975:15"/> hrſt'ned-out of that <hi>rode-way,</hi> by His good Hand with us, as <hi>Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodome.</hi> And God forbid we ſhould looke towards it any more, unleſſe with loathing; as one ſaid of that City of Gods Curſe, <hi>Rome,</hi> when he left it, and had ſet his backe upon it, <hi>Roma vale,</hi> &amp;c.
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rome farewell, againe I will Thee ſee,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>When Baud, Villaine, Raunter, I am reſolv'd to bee.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And now, Sir, we are come neare you, and muſt yet come nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, for we muſt take-in here at the cloſe of this, what we purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly omitted at the beginning or entrance upon it; That wee may ſhew the Reader, the ground of your Confidence (ſuch as it is) That we were not able to hold forth the truth of our way, and walke therein, Why? Becauſe it is different from, if not contrary to your way and walke, which is the ſame, as we fully underſtand now with Mr <hi>H.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee muſt be larger here that we may be plainer, ſo as he who run's may reade us and underſtand us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>THus it was, and this the Truth of the matter; vvhile you were enjoyning us our taske you were pleaſed to inſtance, ſhall we ſay, or not rather to glory in Mr <hi>Hs,</hi> vvho had taken-up Sheild and Buckler, as your great Champion to maintaine the Truth of your way, vvherein he had done ſo worthily, ſad you, that though there vvas one found, vvho made reply to his firſt booke (as you call it, we as was ſaid muſt call it, The vvorke of his fleſh) yet there was not one found, that would undertake to Anſwer his ſecond, being a matter as you thought too high for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker.</p>
               <p>To this we replyed nothing, having indeed nothing to reply, For we never heard of the man before; but ſpeaking of theſe things, as our Duty vvas, to our Miniſter at our meeting, as the manner is, and deſiring his counſell and beſt helpe about it; for wee thought it very unbecoming our profeſſion, our way and walke, And very unanſwerable to all that, which our Lord God
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118975:16"/> hath ſhewed us, wrought for us, and in us, if vvee ſhould ſit ſtill, now looking one upon another, and keepe ſilence in ſuch matters as theſe, being ſo charged to ſpeake to them, and to ſpeake-out; elſe you vvould ſay, for ſo you ſaid, you would take ſilence for a grant, That our way was nought, vvee did not ſpeake for it, it was becauſe we could not, vvee had nought to ſay for it. In the midſt the Debate of theſe matters, mention was made of <hi>M H,</hi> and of the ſweet reliſh his name had at your tongues end, vvhich made ſome of us to thinke he vvas another <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> Some <hi>groat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one,</hi> and indeed ſo he is, as he was among the people, being as vvee may heare afterwards, the <hi>Maſter</hi> of the <hi>Herd.</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding vvee muſt not conceale this, That when our Paſtour heard that Gentleman named and boaſted of by you, he ſtood as a man, vvee know not whether more <hi>wondring</hi> or <hi>greiving,</hi> (ſo deare are his reſpects to you, Sir, if you could ſee it) for he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, he more than doubted, This would greatly diſparage your Name and your Cauſe; and he added this, which he made very cleare unto us, That many men had done unworthily, but that Gentleman exceeded them all; O how hee vaunteth himſelfe, <hi>ſpeaking of his owne</hi> in every line! his <hi>Mode,</hi> who is an advocate for a Nationall Church; oh his monſtrous concluſions! his wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted quotations! his uncouth Philoſophie! his conſequentiall blaſphemie! as a worthy Divine ſpeakes upon another account. O the <hi>vomit</hi> caſt upon the Scriptures, and our Deare Lords prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe! O the filth he belcheth out upon <hi>D. D.</hi> which modeſtie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids us to expreſſe. Many have done moſt unworthily, this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman exceedeth them all; worſe than the worſt, as impudent as impudence it ſelfe. No man, ſaid you, anſwers his ſecond booke, <note n="*" place="margin">This was written before the Authour knew any other Anſwer to Mr. Hs. but by D. D.</note> It is, thinke we, becauſe the firſt anſwer was ſo full and cleare, and ſo <hi>mauled</hi> the man, That had he not been ſo impudent as was ſaid, and animated by the Spirit of the world, he had not roſe-up the ſecond time: But his old-father and great Maſter found him more worke to doe for his children and ſervants the men of the world, and he muſt <hi>doe that, which he hath ſeene with his father:</hi> And being bound to ſuch a Maſter he muſt obey, and he that hath ſuch a <hi>Driver</hi> muſt run. Our Miniſter (for ſo he ſaid at that time) put himſelfe to the loſſe of a little time in reading-his <hi>worke of the</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118975:16"/> 
                  <hi>fleſh,</hi> and paid that charge fully and with advantage by reading the Drs Anſwer thereunto; Yet for the worke it ſelfe he could hardly ſay of it, what <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaid of <hi>Seneca; If you looke upon</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Si inſpicias il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ut paganus Chriſtiane ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, ſi ut Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianus paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicé.</note> 
                  <hi>him as an heathen, then he ſeemes to write like a Chriſtian; but if you looke upon him as a Chriſtian, then he writeth as an heathen:</hi> So ſaid our Paſtour at that time. Quickly after ſome of us did read the man our ſelves, hearing ſo contrary and various a report of him, yours for his goodneſſe, and ſoundneſſe; our Paſtours for his badneſſe, and rottenneſſe. And truely when we conſidered the portion of Scripture he tooke to prove Free Admiſſion of all to the Lord's Table; We may take that Learned Man's words, which <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Owen pag.</hi> 189.</note> he applies to Mr <hi>B:</hi> and apply them to this Gentleman Mr <hi>Hs;</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>He made mention of that portion of Scripture,</hi> Mark 14. 23. <hi>That he might have the honour of cutting his owne throate, and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his owne Cauſe;</hi> or rather God in His righteous Judgement hath forced him to open his mouth to his owne ſhame. Indeed, Sir, theſe are our thoughts, be pleaſed to take them in paſſage.</q> That he your ſaid Champion, and Leader of the <hi>Herd,</hi> underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king from ſacred Writ to cleare your way, hath extremely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded it, ſo marred the very face of it, caſt ſuch a ſpewing upon it againſt his will, that we can hardly thinke, that any one of a ſound mind will walke in it. And wee ſhould looke upon it as a glorious providence, That the ſaid Gentleman hath undertaken your matters, for now we are perſwaded, that all the Miniſters of that perſwaſion, ſhall be fully manifeſted now, and their folly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all men, as Mr <hi>Hs.</hi> now is; and as yours will be, if you look not well to it, which, the God of all Grace, give you grace to doe, Amen.</p>
               <p>So now Sir, in the ſtrength of the Lord wee are girding our ſelves unto our worke you have enjoyned us, <hi>Probé doctus qui probus eſt;</hi> in theſe matters under Debate between us, <hi>He is lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned enough, who is honeſt enough;</hi> for if he hath <hi>Logicke</hi> enough to hold forth this in the <hi>Negative,</hi> that foure-feeted ſwine muſt not have admittance into your Parlour, bed-chamber or cloſet, are not comely gueſts to ſit with Saints at a common Table; then he hath not <hi>honeſty</hi> enough if he reſolves not this in the <hi>Negative</hi> alſo, That two-footed ſwine are not to be admitted to the Lord's
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118975:17"/> Table, to communicate with Saints there. <hi>Si natura negat facit indignatio verſum, If nature deny, yet indignation will make a man a Poet,</hi> was ſaid of old. So wee ſay now, the indignation we have againſt the horrid doings in Gods Houſe, at the Lords Table, committed by the Stewards there, will make us <hi>Logicians</hi> good enough, for the argueing of theſe matters, and rendring them an abomination to every godly man. So we have concluded, he is a <hi>Logician</hi> good enough at theſe matters, who is honeſt enough. And ſo we proceed.</p>
               <p>Beſides we know of Whom to aske Wiſedome and ſtrength and all; Therefore, though we may be every way wanting, we may want gifts and parts, and thoſe acquired abilities, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by labour and induſtry have gained in a full meaſure, Yet <hi>bleſſed be God</hi> and <hi>Father,</hi> for what He hath meated-forth unto us <hi>ſeverally as He will.</hi> 1 Cor: 12. 11. Math: 25. 15. Eph: 4. 7. and ſhewne us the way <hi>unto Himſelfe,</hi> the <hi>Fountaine</hi> and <hi>Spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> of all, whence we may have continuall ſupply for asking, as our needs require, ſo be we <hi>leane</hi> upon Him, <hi>keepe His Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements,</hi> and doe <hi>thoſe things which are pleaſing in His ſight,</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting no confidence in the fleſh at all, for He will not be <hi>All in all to us,</hi> till He hath made us nothing at all in our ſelves. Wee are wofully weake, when we relie on our owne ſtrength: And Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly ſtrong, when we relie upon Him, who alone is the ſtrength of His people; If God be with us, let the weake ſay they are ſtrong. It is the Cauſe of God, of His Chriſt, of His Spouſe, and Houſhold; He hath, He doth, He will helpe, <hi>Si natura negat;</hi> if nature be at a ſtand and can doe nothing, Grace is never at a ſtand, it doth all, and all freely like it ſelfe, without our <hi>money</hi> or <hi>money-worth.</hi> Wee, as all the Faithfull in the World, ſerve a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Maſter; None like Him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He findes His ſervants worke to doe, and findes them hands to doe it; He doth His ſervants worke Himſelfe, and given them wages for doing of it. So no matter what be the tongue, ſo He be the Guide; or the pen, ſo He be the Hand. Therefore having ſo cleare a Call to it, we will haſten to the worke. Though <hi>non ſunt haec litigandi tempora ſed orandi,</hi> theſe times call for prayer rather. But the wiſe God hath diſpoſed it ſo, and will enable for this, and not let the other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118975:17"/> for prayer hath gott more victories than Diſputings have done. And vve doe not doubt but prayer will doe its part now.</p>
               <p>And this may remove the checke in the way which is, That up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on due obſervation, there is little good done by Diſputes of this Nature. One amongſt us doth remember; That going with his Miniſter keeping his turne at a Lecture, you know where, he mett with that honeſt man the Diſputer of the Country Mr. <hi>N.</hi> And after ſome houres debate, about a Nationall Church, (his Theame alwayes, together with Infant Baptiſme, and free Admiſſion by Priviledge thereof) the hearers went away as wiſe as they came; onely all the Advantage that was, was wheeled about to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and wicked-mans ſide, ſo be he were borne in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and baptized there, If waſhed, though a ſwine, all was well, and his right to all Church Communions unqueſtionable. Though wee haſten, what can be, to a cloſe of this, yet wee will take-in this in paſſage to Informe the Reader, That this good Man fetcheth all his ſtrong Arguments, as arrowes out of a qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſo a worthy Divine told one of us, whereby he argueth for free Admiſſion of all to the Lords Table: Dogges and Swine and all, (for if all be admitted, then all ſuch will be there) from their Birth-priviledge, they were baptized, therefore <hi>eo nomine</hi> to be admitted. This will be our Theame in due place, for once and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine wee ſhall meete with it, onely this here we would ſpeake unto it And</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <p>TRuely, intending heartily the Readers information, as plaine and rude in knowledge as our ſelves are, vvee would make an homely ſuppoſition here; for ſo, haply, wee plaine men may prevaile more than by argumentation, ſo little is our skill that way. Wee would ſuppoſe now a foure-footed ſwine ſitting with this Saint (ſuch he is in our account, wee hope, and in his Lords account alſo) at his Table, in his Hall, or Parlour. <hi>Spectatum admiſſi riſum teneatis amici?</hi> Our good Friends, Could ye for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare laughing, beholding ſuch a <hi>ſwine,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>Saint</hi> ſitting together? <hi>Spectatum admiſſi ſletum teneatis amici?</hi> Our Deare Friends, Can yee forbeare weeping, yea bitter mourning, and yet
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118975:18"/> approove your ſelves Freinds of Chriſt, and Followers of God as Deare Children, beholding ſuch gueſts as theſe, <hi>Believers</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidells; Diſciples</hi> and <hi>Drunkards; Holy-Ones</hi> and worſe than the worſt <hi>Heathens; Saints</hi> and <hi>Swine,</hi> vile and loaſome Ones as Sin and Satan can poſſibly make them, little better than <hi>Raunters,</hi> not halfe ſo hanſome and comely as <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſitting in their own cloathes, but not in their <hi>Right minde</hi> at the Lords Table? put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>the Cup to the Mouth,</hi> as boldly venterouſly, and impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as hee did <hi>the bottle,</hi> Hab: 2. 15. <hi>Poyſon</hi> Montanus renders it, as pious and Learned Mr <hi>Greenhill</hi> tells us on <hi>Ezek: 16. pag.</hi> 281. Can yee forbeare weeping, beholding all this? All theſe diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours put upon the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>who Loved you,</hi> and <hi>gave Himſelfe for you;</hi> and <hi>waſhed you in His own blood?</hi> And then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted you Himſelfe, to be his gheſts at his owne Table, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> Can you? Wee thinke ye cannot forbeare weeping; beholding ſuch an affront offered to your Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in His owne houſe, by His Stewards there at His owne Table; Is it not more provoking, if more can be, than once it was, when they ſett their <hi>Threſhold by</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 43. 8. <hi>Adhibendo 111 ditauenes ſuas ad. praecepta mea.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the Lords Threſhold's,</hi> and <hi>their poſts by His poaſts;</hi> that is, as <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> there <hi>mateing the wiſdome of God with the follyes of men?</hi> Wee thinke theſe horrid Doings at the Lords Table more provoking; but judge yee.</p>
               <p>Once more; Can ye forbeare weeping or <hi>ſighting with the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your loynes?</hi> while yee behold ſo many poore wretches (poore indeed, miſerably poore, becauſe ſo rich in conceite, <hi>Rev:</hi> 3. 17. and now, in conceite too; ſo highly dignified and advanced, though indeed as <hi>Haman</hi> was upon the Gallowes) ſitting together, and drinking poyſon one after another, as greedily as the Drunkard doth ſweet Wine? <hi>If wee long after one another in the bowels of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Phill 1. 8. Vide Zanchi.</note> wee cannot but ſhew it to thoſe, who having no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of themſelves, can have no bowells for themſelves, nor their Miniſters, we feare, any for them.—But wee will not prevent our ſelves: This is the chiefeſt Head of our controverſie. Onely meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with this good Man, and knowing his <hi>Genius,</hi> wee could not doe leſſe than what wee have done: For wee would have no good Man, whom we would faine account a Saint, be of Mr <hi>Humph:</hi> perſwaſion: This man is looked upon by all the Godly, we thinke, as a <hi>ſtarre</hi> in our <hi>heaven;</hi> and wee looke upon him as ſuch an one
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118975:18"/> too, yet wee may ſpeake of him, as wee have found him, to be (yet love and eſteeme him never the leſſe) moving ſometimes excen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trically, and out of his ſpheare; and as one that never read holy <hi>Tindalls</hi> good Letter to his Deare Brother <hi>Frith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A ſhort word more, and ſo to adde to that we were ſaying; That this carries all; Wee are borne in a Church, and Baptized there. Why it is the <hi>fac Totum,</hi> the <hi>One thing neceſſary,</hi> the onely thing required, ſo farre as wee can read or heare; To give us right to, <hi>ſeize-on</hi> and <hi>delivery</hi> of all Church Priviledges: If we are borne in a Church and Baptized, which neceſſarily followes, then wee have enough, for <hi>eo nomine</hi>—whereunto in its proper place; For with the Men of Mr <hi>Hs:</hi> perſwaſion, To Deny the Lords Supper to Baptized perſons, though never ſo deboyſed ones, is as ſilly, yea injuriouſly done, as for a ſchollar readily to grant the premiſſes, and willfully to Deny the Concluſion. But</p>
               <p>This now comes to be enquired into and debated-on. What the iſſue will be, the Lord knowes. He will have Glory ſure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, <hi>For that cleane thing,</hi> as worthy Mr <hi>Huit</hi> upon <hi>Dan:</hi> phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it, <hi>He can extract out of our filthineſſe,</hi> whether wee will or no. But this is commonly the fate of all <hi>Mouth-Diſputations</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us Country-folke, It <hi>engendreth ſtrife,</hi> for comming neare together to diſpute our matters, ſtrife ariſeth about words, then wee fall-off from the maine buiſneſſe, or leave it, as papers, in a flame. Indeed Diſputes among us, (whereto wee ignorant, ones are marveilouſly inclined) who can better manage a ſpade, and hold to the Plough much better than to an Argument, ſerve to ſtirre, or blow-up a ſparke to a Coake, and the coale to a flame. Thus too commonly. And then how <hi>great a wood,</hi> a <hi>little fire kindleth?</hi> The Doings now adayes, and <hi>Doatings</hi> upon ſome que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions make full proofe thereof.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding here is the Comfort; there is a Remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all this. The good Lord ſhew it us, and make application of it to us. Amen.</p>
               <p>Before wee cloſe wee will obſerve worthy Mr: <hi>Baxters</hi> words, for moſtly they are very cleare, teaching, and weighty when he ſpeakes of matters neceſſary for us Country-folke to know and underſtand; theſe are his words; <hi>Points controverted are better written than preached; and read than heard.</hi> And your ſelfe ſaid
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118975:19"/> well; Note downe your Allegations and proofes, and ground them upon Scripture. This wee ſhall endeavour to doe looking up to Him, who leads us into all Truth, and teacheth the ſimple folke his way, ſo as they now become <hi>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les,</hi> and ſo are made wiſe indeed, <hi>ſhall not erre therein.</hi> Truly wee have ſtudiouſly minded this thing, how to make this our undertaking, to become a <hi>worke of Faith,</hi> and <hi>Labour of Love!</hi> Wee remembred heartily there is <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 4. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> much <hi>Doating</hi> now adayes about queſtions, ſo as wee make cleare proofe, as the greeke word is, <hi>wee are ſicke</hi> and languiſhing: wee ſooner diſpute about Faith than live by Faith; Wee talke more of Godlineſſe, than of being ſo indeed. Whence it was, That Saint of God on Earth now in Heaven, old Mr <hi>Dod</hi> never loved to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in Controverſies, giving this Reaſon, <hi>He found his heart the worſe, when he did.</hi> Wee ſee then what wee ought to doe, looke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>up to God more <hi>earneſtly, ſtretching-out</hi> our prayers unto him; <note place="margin">Luke 22. 44. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> That wee may move in all meekneſſe; knowing <hi>wee are no more freed from all errour, than wee are from all ſinne; And that one man may conceive him-ſelfe as certaine of his errour,</hi> as <hi>another Man of his knowledge;</hi> That ſo our Controverſie here may be wholy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged, in reference to practiſe, not to parties; not that wee (for what are wee? but breathing peices of earth, and little better in ſight than ſo many Crumbles of duſt) not that wee, but <hi>Truth</hi> may have the victory; and our Diſpute may ſerve wholy to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, in our ſelves, and the Readers, the <hi>power of Godlineſſe.</hi> For vurely Errour from the Truth is beſt confuted, by holding-forth of the Truth, and clearing it to the World, That our ſoules doe cleave to it, delight-in it, and Cannot but doe all wee can for it.</p>
               <p>That the purity, Truth, and goodneſſe of our Doctrines may be held forth, and adorned by the Truth of our practiſe, purity, and godlineſſe of our lives, is the Prayer of all the Godly in the whole World, Miniſters and People, whereunto they with our ſelves, adde that Signall Concluſion, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
